[Music]
and we are live
so good evening and good day everyone i
hope you are all well welcome to episode
2 of
ask abhijit so yesterday i took a lot of
questions that were asked
below before the live stream
and because of that i ended up missing a
lot of the live
chat questions that you asked me and
some of you even
purchased some super chat stickers so it
was a learning experience for me for the
first live stream
and so thank you very much to everyone
who asked me these questions
and thank you especially to those who
purchased super chat
i appreciate it very much and today i'm
gonna make this a completely
uh interactive session i'm gonna take
your
questions that you're asking me in real
time so
let's begin and let me take this
question
from yeshwanth so yeshwanth asks
where did r1a originate various reports
claim different places including india
iran etc why is it now dominant
point of view by ait goods ketians
and other responsible for the gene flow
etc right
so for those of you who don't know r1a
is a genetic lineage
it's a patrilineal genetic lineage it's
called a haplogroup in genetic
terminology
so it's a lineage that is passed on from
father to sun
it's a specific genetic mutation
and the genetic
research shows that this lineage is at
least 15 to 20
000 years old and there is a lot of
controversy about where
it has originated and the reason for the
controversy is this
that r1a is the world's most
successful extended family it's the most
successful genetic lineage that is known
to humankind it's population
today is probably more than one billion
people
and there are two clusters geographical
clusters where
most of these people of this particular
lineage live
one is the indian subcontinent
and the other one is uh eastern europe
and northern europe so poland
germany ukraine russia that that area
so these are two clusters geographical
clusters where you find
the majority of the males who have this
specific genetic lineage
now the question so therefore historians
and geneticists etc have
hypothesized that this particular
genetic lineage
is the one that is associated with the
spread of indo-european languages
and culture so in essence the people
who originally carried this lineage
are the original rn invaders and
that the the the theory is that
these people invaded india about two and
a half
thousand about about three thousand
years three and a half thousand years
before present
from eastern europe and from central
asia
so that is the prevailing
consensus opinion among imminent
historians right now
so there are a number of questions about
it first of all there is no
evidence of where this particular
lineage has originated from so every
genetic lineage
has a certain geographical origin
and how do we determine the origin we
find the region where there is the most
genetic diversity within that lineage
so the question is where do we find the
most genetic diversity
within the r1a lineage
and it is most likely
to be india so there is research being
done right now within india by
geneticists
uh some research is being done a lot of
research is being done
some papers will be published hopefully
soon
and what is most likely going to happen
what is most likely going to emerge from
this research
is that india is the homeland of the r1a
lineage
which would come which would completely
reverse the narrative
that is uh currently prevailing that the
aryans invaded india
from the west if r1a is the homeland
if india is the homeland of the r1 a
lineage it would indicate that the
expansion of r1a happened from outs from
within india outwards
to the west therefore it would mean that
there was an invasion but from india
into europe
so that is why there is a controversy
because uh
the consensus opinion is the is the
reverse of that and because
the academic system the academic
environment the academic milieu
is very much euro centric as of now
because all the research
all the the major funding and the major
uh research institutes genetic
institutes etc are all in the west
and they are invested in protecting a
certain
worldview and a certain narrative so
that is the reason for this controversy
and they are funding many people in
india many uh journalists many writers
and therefore uh there is this conflict
that is
going on right now between the
proponents of one narrative and the
prophets of another narrative
i am not interested in any narrative i
am interested in seeing what the
research
tells us so most likely the research is
going to show that r1a
is indian in origin now you asked a
question about
most scythian skeletons that you find
throughout eurasia
most of the male sketchy skeletons have
this r1a lineage
so it's clear that the sketchings were
very much part of this expansion
whether it's out of india or whether out
of europe we will soon find out
but yes the sketchings definitely are
very closely genetically culturally
and ethnically related to the indian
people
so that is in brief about our thank you
yeshwanth for this question
right i have another question here
one second
[Music]
so this is by rohan chaudhary rohan
thank you very much for purchasing the
super chat
uh the question is do you have any idea
about kumari kandam
the continent that was below india is it
a myth
so as of now we don't know whether it is
or not the the story the the
recorded history so to say in um
especially in tamil nadu is that there
was
a large expanse of land that has now
been swallowed up by the sea
this was south of the uh current
geographical extent of the indian
subcontinent
and possibly during the last ice age or
so this
this particular expanse of land was
above the sea
and uh eventually it went under the sea
and that's why
and so that's the story so apparently
it's according to this
uh according to this remembered history
the tamil people used to live in this uh
extended part of the indian subcontinent
and it is called
kumari condom so that is
the the
remembered history do we have any
evidence of this as of now no we do not
if you look at the uh geological
maps of the subsurface
extent of the indian subcontinent which
extends below the sea to the south it
doesn't look like there is any such
any such submerged land from the
evidence that we have as of now
now we know that geology is something
that is always
changing it's always in motion we
recently had the great andaman
earthquake that completely
changed the shapes of islands it
it helped certain islands emerge higher
than the the higher than where they were
it made some islands go a little bit
into the sea and it could definitely
change the sub
sub ocean subsurface geography of the
of the ocean of the ocean floor so
if this continent was above the
above the ocean more than 10 000 years
ago then it's possible that it sank
below the ocean
and some geogra some some earthquake or
something may have disturbed
uh that part of the that part of the sub
sub ocean region and maybe that's why
we're not able to see it there is a
possibility
but from the evidence that we have right
now it looks like
we do not have sufficient evidence to
to take this idea as of now from a
scientific from a narrow scientific
perspective
to take it seriously as of now but i am
open
to finding new evidence that may prove
it because see the thing is that
there are many places where people have
very old memories very long memories
of things that happened thousands of
years ago and eventually they are
discovered to be true
so is this one of those things that may
be discovered to be true in the future
yes definitely it is possible so let's
wait and watch and
hopefully when one finds evidence of
this
so thank you for the question
all right let me find this
this is a question by way above
chaudhary thank you very much
so the question is do you think the
vedic civilization will continue to
exist
or cease because of abrahamic
thank you above thank you very much uh
so the vedic civilization which is our
civilization
it still exists to some extent we i
would not
call india as it is today to be a
civilization anymore
a civilization has certain
characteristics
and india is today merely a nation state
it is no longer a civilization
a civilization is a net exporter of
culture so it has a cultural sphere of
influence
that far exceeds its geographical
boundaries
and that's what india has used to be for
thousands of years
india has exported culture throughout
asia and throughout the rest of the
world
for thousands of years and a
civilization also has other
characteristics like it is extremely
prosperous
it has a strong military it has a strong
military sphere of influence
it has cultural and uh national
institutions that are
rooted in its own indigenous culture so
it's consideration to be rooted in its
own culture
its judiciary its legislator legislature
its all of its other institutions should
be rooted in its own values in its own
morals and its
own culture so that is not what you find
in india today
today india's uh institutions
india's constitution india's laws are
all western
in origin and in nature the morality
that they follow is a western morality
so it's like we are still ruled by the
foreigners even 70 years after we
supposedly got our independence and our
constitution defines
india as a nation-state not as a
civilization
state so i would say that as of today
india is not a civilization india is
something
lesser than a civilization will vedic
civilization continue to exist i believe
it that we have a very strong chance
that it should continue to exist
if we are able to reclaim our land
reclaim our
culture and re-establish it
as the primary culture
of our homeland i don't think there is
anything wrong with that
every every nation follows its own laws
and it has its own values and its own
morality and its own
and their institutions they follow the
culture that has been part of that
land for for as long as it has existed
you find this in the islamic countries
you find this in the west
many countries are openly christian
countries most of the middle eastern
countries
are officially islamic countries so i
don't see why
india can again revert to being a vedic
country it doesn't mean that we gonna
kill the minorities or anything vedic
religion hindu religion
has been the most respectful and
tolerant towards all other cultures
so there is no uh question
of uh of of or of
the the kind of narrative that is
peddled of hindu
supremacy or hindu majoritarianism or
any such thing
so i would say that vedic civilization
could continue need to exist i hope it
does
but certain steps will have to be taken
for this to happen
so thank you very much weber for this
question
all right let me see what else we have
all right this is a question by phobic
uh did indians
and chinese know about each other during
the mahabharata era
if yes how were their relations
so according to the best evidence that
we have
the mahabharata era must have happened
at least 6000 years before today
and if you look at the history of china
as as
a distinct culture and civilization
it is about two and a half or three
thousand years old
or if you want to be charitable they are
three and a half thousand years old
as a distinct culture so china has a
history which is three and a half
thousand years old
the mahabharata happened most likely at
least six thousand years before today
so the mahabharata the predates the
chinese there were no chinese and there
was no china when the mahabharat
happened
and therefore they there is no
question of indians and chinese knowing
each other each other at the time
because india did exist as a distinct
and very powerful and very influential
civilization
but china did not exist at the time so
that is the brief answer
to your question
okay let me see some more questions
okay this is by dhruva and india ghosh
are the yazidis and kurds ancient
hindus so the kurds the kurdish people
are muslims today they are
classified as an iranian ethnic
as an iranian people as people who are
part of
so-called greater iran so their
ethnicity is iranian which is
essentially indo-iranian
which means that they like i have said
previously the iranians
are if you look at it genetically from a
genetic perspective
the iranians are part of the same
ethnicity as the indians the afghans
pakistanis nepalese etc
so that is the extent of this ethnicity
and by the same argument
the goods would also be part of the same
ethnicity now where the ancient hindus
culturally
we don't have sufficient evidence to
come to a
definite conclusion about that because
the pre-islamic history
of most uh islamic
ethnic groups has essentially been wiped
out we don't know what they were before
so about the kurds we don't know what
their history was before they became
muslims what was their culture like
they most likely practiced
zoroastrianism because they
are part of the uh iranian cultural
sphere
so i would say that they practiced zero
zoroastrianism before islam
but before zoroastrian zoroastrianism
what was it
it would most likely have been vedic
hinduism because
the iranians the persians themselves
are an offshoot of the various vedic
clans they are the
parshwa clans they are the they are the
descendants of the parshwa clan
of the rigvedic peoples so the word
persia comes from the word
parshu and the word parshwa comes from
the sanskrit word parshu
which means the battle axe so i would
imagine that these people
this clan preferred to use the battle
axe in warfare or something like that
that's why they are called they were
called the parshwa people
and they that name gave gave rise to the
land
that they colonized which is now known
as persia their ancient capital was
known as parshvapur
the greeks called it persepolis it's the
city that alexander the great
burned in a night of drunken rampage
so right so that's what that's about the
kurds
about the yazidis uh they practice
a religion that appears to be
monotheistic
but it has very uh unmistakable
polytheistic roots
uh you find elements of nature worship
they worship the serp i mean the serpent
is a sacred symbol for them
the peacock is a sacred symbol for them
that is
very reminiscent of shaivite hinduism
and they worship fire which is again
very reminiscent of hinduism the worship
of agni
agni is one of the principal vedic gods
so there are unmistakable elements of
a pre of an ancient of a more ancient
religion which was
practiced which seems to be very very
similar
to hinduism today they have to pretend
like it's
a monotheistic religion and they have
added some
elements superficial elements of
monotheism
to the religion so that they in order
for them to survive
in the environment that they are in uh
genetically
and ethnically again they seem to be
part of the uh
greater iranian population which would
again
say which would again indicate that they
have the same cultural roots
as the iranians and the kurds so i would
say that their origins are most likely
indo-aryan or indo-iran
iranian which means that their deep
ancestry
would be culturally
indian or culturally vedic if you go
back several thousand years
so that's the answer to this question
thank you very much for this question
all right let me find some more
questions
okay
so this is a question from subhajit pal
if contact is ever established with
intelligent alien life forms how would
linguistic flourish
is a subject of study and research
so this reminds me of that movie what's
it called
arrival i believe which were which dealt
with
the linguistic aspects of communicating
with an alien with an alien
civilization so if contact is ever
established with
intelligent alien life forms we would
definitely need to find some means of
communication
and that would depend on their biology
and their means of communication so
we humans primarily communicate via
sound
and sight now what kind of biology would
aliens have
would they also communicate by sound or
would they have a different means of
communication
so it is a very speculative hypothetical
thing but definitely they would need
some form of communication
we would have to find some mutually
intelligible form of communication
and all communication eventually boils
down to linguistics
so i would imagine it would it would
finally bring linguistics into the
into the realm of science so as of today
linguistics is a very
it's it's called it is described or
portrayed as a science
but it's a very unscientific subject
uh linguists deal
in lot of speculation and there is a lot
of consensus building so if
sufficient people agree to a certain
narrative then that narrative becomes
the officially accepted
dogma in linguistics today so if we were
to
make contact with an alien civilization
then we would have to bring linguistics
into the realm of science
in order to actually make it work so
that would be a very interesting uh
happening it would definitely flourish
as a subject of research
great question
okay let me see some more questions
all right jaya dikshit uh please tell us
about ancient indian education system
can we use the system today in india and
throw the macallan system
out so this is a question that many
people asked
yesterday as well the ancient
indian education system was primarily
based around
temples which is very counter-intuitive
because today we see temples as places
of worship
so temples were places of worship but
they were also cultural and social
centers and so and centers of education
so in ancient india before
the events of the past 1000 years you
had temples
everywhere every town every village
every locality
had a temple usually these would be
small temples with ones
with one single priest or brahmana who
would carry out the duties
but there would be places where you had
larger temples and every temple
was not just a place of worship it was a
school
the local children would get an
education over there so basically
the smallest temples would impart basic
education
uh language grammar basic mathematics
and things like that
the language of education was always
sanskrit you always had two languages of
education
one was sanskrit and one was your local
language so
there is this historian called dharampal
who was a gandhian who lived in the 20th
century
he spent a number of years in the uk he
spent a number of years
in britain after india's independence
and he accessed a lot of the historical
data that the british had collected
about india's education system before
they imposed the macallan system
on india so this data is from the 19th
century essentially
so the rampal accessed a great amount of
this data he analyzed it
and he wrote a book called the go the
beautiful tree i believe in which he has
shown
what kind of education system was still
prevalent in the 19th century
so what he found from the british data
which is the british
collected is that temples were the
places of education education was
provided to every child
girls boys everybody all the jhatis all
the varnas the so-called castes
everybody got the education the
education was always free
it was subsidized by the local king or
ruler or whoever it was
so you never had to pay for education in
the small temples
you had basic education like i said in
larger temples and bigger cities
you would find that you would get
somewhat higher education
and you had the great temples in in
certain places
where you were you would get really high
education and then you had the great
viharas
monasteries and then you had the great
universities of india the great vishwa
vidal vidyalayas so there were so many
of these
nalanda taksha shilla telhara udantapuri
vikramashila
sharda peat and so many more we only
know a few
today but there were so many more of
these and these
great universities was where you would
get the highest education
available anywhere in the world so you
would be taught
subjects like pharmacology toxicology
advanced mathematics
calculus in finite series uh
trigonometry
astronomy and and much more and also
philosophical subjects you had so many
schools
of philosophical thought in india uh
starting from charwaka
veda vedanta mansa and so many more so
all of this
was taught all of this was researched
there are many schools of thought there
are many great scholars
and this is the education system that
india had and
so the small temples did double as
gurukuls essentially
and so on so this education system was
spread throughout the length and the
breadth of this country
and all the education was free it was
open to anybody
and in the great universities the only
impediment
to entering was your intellect and your
knowledge
so you would have entrance tests and if
you pass the entrance test if you were
found to be at that
level of intellectual of intellect
and if you had that amount the amount of
knowledge required
to gain entry then you would gain entry
you would be given admission
and you would be imparted education for
free
in these universities and anybody could
could come to the universities and
be and study there many chinese pilgrims
are known to have
studied in india's great universities
even greek pilgrims have done that
and so on keithians too so it was open
to everyone
even to foreigners even to their people
who did not identify as
indians or hindus it was open to all
the only requirement was that you need
to you needed to be
at that level of intellect so that is
the kind of education system we had it
was the greatest
education system the world has ever seen
today's education system
is i don't have uh sufficiently
strong words to describe how bad it is
it is it is rubbish
it is a pale imitation of the western
education system
and let me tell you about the west if
you look at the united states the
education system they have
imposes an enormous burden on the
children an enormous financial burden
on students especially higher education
i mean every
on average just the average student who
passes out of this education system at
the college level
incurs a debt of about 44 000 u.s
dollars
and then they have to work for many
years to pay this debt off
so the western education system
especially the american one
is just is all about commercializing
education
education has become a commodity degrees
have become commodities
you pay a certain amount of money you
will get a admission
and you may even find unfortunately
there have been certain scandals
in the ivy league universities recently
in which it was found that
you could actually pay to get a phd and
you could actually you could actually
purchase degrees there
so that is the state of the education
system in the united states
it is all about money it's a capitalist
system
i am not advocating marxism or socialism
i'm just saying that commercializing
education is very wrong
it's it's going to have a very
deleterious effect on society
so we are currently trying to copy that
system which is
which is not good at all it's going to
have very
adverse effects on indian society in the
long term
in the long in the long term so is it
possible to bring back the old system
it would it would require a great deal
of reforms
over a certain period of time but it
would be good if we could do that
because we had the best system in the
world
and it's been destroyed by the british
and we have
not taken the initiative to bring it
back
so that's the answer
okay let me find some more
[Music]
okay this is a question by aditya
bharadwaj thank you aditya
what are the significant places for
excavation in modern india
has there been any update on deciphering
the underwater remains in the dwarka
basin
so the first part of the question is
what are the significant places for
excavation
in modern india i'll tell you what
wherever you are right now you take a
shovel
dig a trench that is 5 to 10 meters deep
and you're gonna find something
interesting from the archaeological
perspective
that's how rich india is in its ancient
history and its archaeology
india's civilization is minimum 10 000
years old
and it was a vast urban population
five thousand or six thousand years
before today so what we know is that the
harappan the so-called harappan phase of
our
of our civilization is essentially
concentrated in
western and northwestern india from
maharashtra
in the south through gujarat to through
madhya pradesh parts of up haryana
punjab
present-day pakistan sindh and presently
afghanistan
and parts of kashmir so this is the
currently accepted extent of the
so-called
harappan phase of our civilization
and we have excavated about one percent
of the known archaeological sites
of the harappan uh era for civilization
the the truth is that the entirety of
india
was an urban civilization and the
harappan part is just what we have so
far
taken notice of if you look at the city
of varanasi
and some archaeological work has been
done there it has been found that
that ancient varanasi was just as
urbanized
and just as ancient as the so-called
harappan
part of part of india and varanasi
actually seems to be even older
than that so that's one example we are
finding places like kilady and other
places in the south
these are not separate civilizations
these are just
things that we have cherry picked once
we start excavating the whole of india
you will find that it was all
interconnected it was all one
vast network throughout the indian
subcontinent
and it was all the same civilization you
had local manifestation of
culture but overall it was one culture
which connected everything
so i would say that the significant
places for excavation are everywhere
every town every village every district
every state
has something unique to contribute to
the archaeological record of india
there are so many incredible places
chandra ketugar
in bengal it's an incredible
archaeological site
and i can guarantee there are lots lots
more in bengal
there are lots more in kalinga presently
orissa many insi in the south
anywhere you go in the south if you're
going to do some digging you're going to
find incredible
findings and once this begins
once archaeology is taken seriously and
money is invested in doing this
we're gonna find that india's
civilization is much older than ten
thousand years it's gonna go
much beyond that so so the significant
places are
everywhere now has there been any update
on deciphering the
underwater remains in dwarka there has
been no progress on that
some archaeological work was done in the
1980s and 90s
it was discovered that the story of the
mahabharata is indeed true
that an ancient city did slide
underwater
most likely because of a powerful
earthquake
where presented is so if you go to the
site of present day modern day dwarka
and you go to the sea the seashore over
there then there is an underwater
underwater submerged city there the old
dwarka the
mahabharata and once this was discovered
archaeological work stopped
for whatever reason because hey we
should not prove that
india's ancient ethios is actually real
history
so the asi has not done has not taken
any initiative on further exploring
dwarka
i am afraid there may even have been
some damage done
to that ancient city because of uh
various
port work and modern construction
activities
i hope it's not too much damaged i
certainly hope that uh
some renewed interest will be shown in
properly exploring and cataloging this
wonderful treasure of ancient india
so that's the answer to your question
aditya thank you so much
all right some more questions
this is by deb how can the chinese
country be broken or simply how could
democracy be installed in china
breaking and throwing away the communist
regime democracy in china would benefit
india
so see democracy is a
is a is a cultural thing certain
countries and certain cultures
are inherently attuned towards being
democratic
and certain countries and certain
cultures are not
in are fundamentally disinclined
towards democracy so if you look at the
history of india
you have the maha janapada era which was
essentially republics
these were democratic republics you had
kings
but those kings essentially were agents
of the people
if you look at the harappan phase of
india's civilization which is like five
six seven thousand years old
you will find this great vast urban
population centers
and you will not see a single palace
you will not see a single royal palace
anywhere which means that there were
no there was no there was no royalty
there may have been governors and
administrators
or even kings by title but they did not
live in a way that was superior to the
ordinary people which indicates you had
a form of democracy even during the
harappan phase of india's
of india civilization so what i'm trying
to say is that india has always been an
inherently democratic culture democracy
is
is natural to the indian people
not the western form of democracy which
we are currently
uh living under but our own
system of democracy which we had evolved
over thousands of years now if you look
at china china has never been a
democracy
china has always been an empire you
always had
imperial dynasties ruling china whether
china has been fragmented at times
and it has been unified at times the
geographical extent of china was always
east
of the so-called great wall of china
today is china
it incorporates a lot of territory that
has been
usurped from other peoples so the
so-called xinjiang region
is not chinese territory historically
tibet has historically never been
chinese manchuria has historically never
been chinese
yunnan is not chinese it is a thai
ethnic geographical region and so on and
so forth
so so the present-day geographical
extent of china is
rather unnatural it is all through the
strength of conquest
now what can be done about china can
democracy be installed in china
i do not think china will ever be
democratic china will always be an
imperialistic
and imperial country even today you have
a so-called marxist socialist system
but it's actually an imperial system the
the person who is
denoted as the president of china is
actually the emperor of china
so it's an imperial system under the
guise of a
socialist marxist state so china is
always going to be
an imperial culture and civilization
now what about the communist regime
which is what you ask
so as of now the communist regime is
very strongly entrenched
in china but if you look at the history
of china over the past
2000 years you see certain patterns that
occur over and over and over again and
what you find it's it's called dynastic
cycles
so you find that a certain dynasty an
imperial dynasty comes to power
and when it comes to power it is
supposed to have the mandate of heaven
because it has
been able to acquire power over the
other or the people of china
and then over time this dynasty becomes
more and more authoritarian and
oppressive
and eventually it suffers a military
defeat
or it suffers an insurrection from
within and it crumbles and falls
so this typically happens every 70 years
or 100 years or so
and then a new and then there is a p a
period of unrest in china
and then a new dynastic cycle emerges
so this is the pattern of history in
china for the past two thousand or so
years
now i would say that the chinese
communist regime is
a new dynasty it is
they they say that it is not a dynasty
it is a socialist state
but it is a socialist state that it is
essentially a dynasty
masquerading as a socialist marxist
state
so i would say that the the pattern that
china has
been observing for the past 200 years
2000 years will definitely be seen again
so at some point in time this regime
will crumble
what would trigger such an event most
likely
if china were to do some sort of
military misadventure
and they were to suffer a military
defeat then
there would be a strong insurrection
from within because the people would see
this regime as having
lost the mandate of heaven and then
its continuation would be very
untenable it would be on very shaky
grounds so
what would possibly trigger the collapse
of the communist regime in the future
is most likely a military misadventure
and a military defeat
now where would this happen one can only
speculate but
that is one way it could happen would
democracy in china benefit india
i would say that india and china have
historically never been adversaries the
past 2000 years india and china have
never been adversaries it's only in the
past
60 or 70 years after the communist
communists came to power
that india and china became rivals so i
would say that
uh if the communists were to go out of
power
it would be beneficial not only for
india but for the whole world
so let's see what happens history is uh
geopolitics is fickle things change very
fast
so let's let's wait and watch right now
we are in a period of great
geopolitical churn this decade
especially is going to see a lot of
changes
possibly in in borders and whatnot so
it's it's an interesting time that we
live in so let's see how it goes
all right let me see
chirag thank you so much
uh lina i missed your super chat let me
see where it is
guys you need to forgive me if i'm
missing some super chats i am still
learning this thing it's only my second
live stream
i'm gonna pick up speed and uh
figure out how this works okay
okay ashwatama
uh can and should sanskrit replace
english as the lingua franca and the
national language unifying india
why people from the world learn chinese
but indians learn languages of the world
very good question
so sanskrit has always
been the unifying language of india
the chola dynasty which is a tamil
dynasty
conquered the entirety of southeast asia
and they spread the propagated sanskrit
over there
as the lingua franca not tamil despite
being a tamil dynasty
which tells you that the entirety of the
indian subcontinent
used sanskrit as the civilizational
language as the unifying language
it is the oldest language known to
humankind
and when india got its independence
there was a serious discussion about
making sanskrit
the national language but our great
prime minister
mr nehru prevailed and he made hindi the
national language of india so i would
say that
india would greatly benefit if sanskrit
were to be restored to its
natural position of being the unifying
language i am not talking about making
about sanskrit supremacy about
sanskritization
everybody has their own
mother tongue india is a very diverse
country lots of different languages
lots of different dialects so i would
say that we should have a two language
policy
one is the civilizational language and
the other is the mother tongue
everybody should learn these two
languages equally well
and all languages should be given equal
importance
but there has to be a unifying
civilizational language
and the the natural candidate for that
the only language that that that
is suitable for that is sanskrit so yes
sanskrit should replace
english as the lingua franca and the
national language we should be
having this conversation in sanskrit it
would be so nice if we could all do that
but we are not currently in a position
to do that i
hope that future generations will
rediscover
the greatness of our own civilization
language
so why do people from india learn
chinese why do people from the world
learn chinese but indians learn
languages of the world
it's because the chinese have more
self-respect than indians as of today
what i mean to say is that the chinese
government
has more self-respect than the indian
government today if you see the chinese
there are daily press conferences in the
in beijing
the external affairs ministry of china
does these press conferences every day
and they only speak in chinese
and if you see india's ministry of
foreign affairs they they do press
conferences
in english which i think is very
shameful you should at least do it in
hindi
so the indian government in the indian
indian
institutions the indian bureaucracy and
the indian establishment
needs to learn to respect its own
culture and history
and i hope that happens someday
someday in the near future as of now we
are stuck in the
in the current scenario but yes we need
to stop
if they are not doing it we need to show
some initiative and start
uh learning our own history
and start learning sanskrit it would be
really beneficial to all of us
so so that's the answer thank you very
much for your question
asim the girl asim thank you so much
so what are the reasons behind the
language of indus valley remaining
undeciphered despite similarity in vedic
indus culture why is the language a
mystery with no connection
with sanskrit what a wonderful fantastic
question
so there is something called
uh the frawley paradox
it's uh its originator is dr david
frawley who is a
very famous indologist he is an american
hindu
a very nice person and a great scholar
so
frauley's paradox says that india has
the world's the world's most
uh extensive ancient literature
which is sunset literature even though
most of india's literature was destroyed
in the burning of our great universities
even though this happened we still have
millions of ancient manuscripts that are
gathering dust
in various uh archives and various
temples and all that
so we have the world's greatest literary
tradition
the oldest literary tradition and we
also have
the one of the world's the world's
greatest ancient uh urban
population center the the greatest
world's greatest
ancient civilization which is the
harappan civilization
and historians would like to would like
us to believe
that this literary tradition that we
have has come from the central asian
step and from europe
and this great population center is
completely different from that
so that is the fraud paradox we have
this great population center
and we have this great literary
tradition in sanskrit and we are
unwilling to put two and two together
and associate these two with each other
so the the the point is that
the language of the indus valley
civilization
the so-called harappan civilization was
most likely
vedic or post-vedic sanskrit
there is no other logical alternative
some
proponents of the aryan invasion theory
or the aryan migration theory soon to be
rn tourism theory
they would like us to believe that this
was a dravidian civilization and
proto-tamil or something like that was
the uh
language of the indus valley region well
what
evidence do you have for this there is
none whatsoever
and there is beginning to emerge
some evidence that the indus valley
script
may be the precursor of the brahmi and
karoshi scripts
which were used to write most ancient
languages in india
primarily sanskrit
now why has this script
not been deciphered yet because nobody
has
see to decipher an ancient script
you need funding you need a think tank
you need to bring a number of brains
together you need to bring a number of
scholars together
and that has never happened in this
country the government has never shown
any
genuine willingness to do this so what's
happening is that you have
isolated scholars trying to do this work
of deciphering the script
but it's so far never happened
and another possible reason may be
that the script that we find in these
ancient
inscriptions may just be a form of
shorthand
and maybe the the people of that era of
our civilization
maybe they used to write the actual
script on paper
on a form of paper or on cloth and maybe
none of that has survived over these
thousands of years
so what we are left with is this form of
shorthand
which is not really the real script that
they used that is also a possibility
so that is of course speculation we
don't have evidence for that
but it is a possibility so what i would
like to see
happen is that we should start using
machine learning and artificial
intelligence
just to start parsing and analyzing this
ancient
whatever uh
evidence of ancient script that we have
collected thus far
and try and see which linguistic
morphology
it matches the most closely so that
could be a good start so we need to
start
using technology to tackle these old
unsolved problems so that's what i would
like to see happen
my strong conviction is that
the people of the harappan era and the
geographical region
they spoke vedic or post-vedic sanskrit
this is definitely a post rigvedic part
post rig vedic
phase of our civilization because if you
see the
rig veda it speaks about a pastoral
india it doesn't speak of any urban
centers at all it speaks about
a rural phase of india's civilization
which must have happened
long before the urban phase of india
civilization which is called the
harappan phase
so i am convinced that the language
of the harappan civilization
was either vedic or post-vedic sanskrit
definitely pre-panini and sanskrit so
let's see i
hope that this mystery will be resolved
sooner rather than later
thank you for the question
all right let me see what else do we
have
okay this is a question from dave what
is the future of this world in terms of
geopolitics
will borders exist in the future or will
the world simply be a big global village
as many says
or will there be something else well
right now the future of the world
is up for grabs we don't know in what
direction things will go
currently as you see big tech companies
are slowly but steadily encroaching upon
the sovereignty of nations so for
example you have something like twitter
which is trying to dictate what people
can say and cannot say
within the geographical sovereign region
of india
so they have encroached they have
come into our nation via the internet
and they are trying to regulate
how we speak and how and what kind of
discussions we can have
so this is a direct challenge on the
sovereignty of india
and of every other nation recently i
believe
facebook said that australian users
would no longer be allowed to use
facebook
because of some law that the government
of australia passed
and i think the australian government
had to retract
that law so they are these big tech
companies are able to exert
pressure on sovereign governments and
they are trying to
bring themselves or position themselves
at the same level as sovereign
governments
so twitter would like to have a dialogue
with the indian government about what
constitutes free speech
so this shows you that sovereignty
is in danger of crumbling and the entire
geopolitical system that we have
may soon become obsolete because of the
intrusive presence of big tech companies
and social media and all that
so that would be one way of making
borders obsolete
the second thing that could happen would
be that
the entire world becomes just one
culture once again because of the
pervasive nature of
internet and the social media so you
have all these narratives that are that
are
funded by billions of dollars of money
and you see these hashtags everywhere
and there's narratives everywhere
and people are beginning to imbibe these
foreign notions
whatever they are so slowly this is this
is a form of
social engineering that has been that is
being done
online and it is very effective
so that could again make borders
obsolete
and if there is uh a future conflict
that could also make the world
and the other the the borders obsolete
so right now things are up for grabs
geopolitically it's a time of great
churn
right now the supremacy of the west is
declining the west is in decline it has
lost
its moorings so to say uh
there used to be a certain way of
thought that the west
is uh civilizationally and morally and
economically
and militarily superior to the east
so that has long since crumbled
and so so the world is currently in a in
a phase of
great upheaval and this decade could
definitely be one of the most important
decades in geopolitics because the
situation that we are in right now
you the world has changed a lot in the
past one and a half years
it has changed beyond what you could
have imagined in
2019 and this is most likely something
that has been
engineered and
the the world's gdp is is declining
most big most big nations are seeing the
gdp decline
china's gdp is shooting up so there is
definitely a bid for
global supremacy that we are witnessing
in real time right now
so the future of the world is up for
grabs i think uh will there be a
conflict in the near future
there could be i believe china may very
well
invade taiwan within the next five to
ten years and
once it it will do that once it is
convinced
that the west is in no la is no longer
in a position to interfere
or to stop them and once china
captures taiwan then their navy will be
free
to come eastwards or sorry to come
westwards which is in the indian ocean
region
and unfortunately india has done nothing
to create a blue water navy
a couple of submarines doesn't cut the
bill by far
so yeah things are changing and let's
see how it goes
there's a lot which could happen in the
near future
right so thank you for the for the
question
all right
okay let's take a physics question it's
by priyanka
can quantum mechanics solve the human
brain mechanism
and can consciousness be described by
particles dual
nature so there is a school of thought
that says that
uh the that that consciousness
is an emergent phenomenon which emerges
from the biochemistry of the brain
and that it has a quantum mechanical
origin
so it is quantum processes inside the
brain
that give rise to an emergent phenomenon
called consciousness so this is
a theory that has been put forward by
roger penrose and one of his
collaborators
uh so yeah there is a school of thought
that says this
it is not proven thus far it is
interesting
but we don't know whether it is true or
not is consciousness
so is so quantum mechanics may possibly
have a role to play
in the human brain mechanism essentially
the entire reality as we see it emerges
from the laws of quantum mechanics how
exactly it happens we are still
trying to understand it we don't have
all the answers quantum mechanics is
fundamentally weird
and we understand very little of it we
know how it works we know how to use it
for calculating
we know how to use it for creating
technologies everything we have today
is most likely is is to some extent at
least
thanks to quantum technologies the
communication that we are doing right
now is would not have been possible
without
technologies that were made possible by
quantum mechanics
so we know how to use it but we don't
know what it is what it is saying to us
okay the second question is can
consciousness be described by particles
dual nature we don't know
we don't even know what consciousness is
we don't even have a definition
of consciousness it is the biggest
mystery
in science right now until now it has
been thought of as a spiritual or
philosophical concept
but now it has become front it has come
front and center in science
so as of now we have absolutely no idea
of what
of what consciousness is there are lots
of
interesting speculations but there is
very little concrete work
being done or concrete theories so so
it's a it's a field of active
investigation as of now
okay let me see
okay string theory what is string theory
so like i said we do not
really understand quantum mechanics and
one of the basic assumptions
in quantum mechanics and in most physics
is that particles
are points so we have done this over
simplification of considering particles
to be
zero dimensional points and all our
calculations are based on that all our
theories are constructed
on the basis on the basis of this
assumption
on the basis of this simplification and
we get very good results
with the theories that we have do give
us very good
uh explanations of how the universe
works
we are able to understand the laws of
physics and the forces
and their interactions very well via the
the
theory via quantum field theory which is
very very
uh successful it's a very successful
theory and yet
there is one very big problem we don't
know how gravity works at the
quantum scale and so to resolve this
problem
string theory was was invented so in
string theory we don't
take particles to be zero dimensional
points
instead we it is postulated that the
entire universe
is composed at the most fundamental
level
of one-dimensional vibrating strings
so that is the fundamental core premise
of string theory and then you use
mathematics to build
that to build upon that and what we have
found is that you
that string theory simply doesn't work
in
ordinary three-dimensional or
four-dimensional space you need
ten dimensions to make the mathematics
of string theory work
so that is a problem and then people
have come up with the ideas like the
compactification of dimensions
and so forth but the real problem with
string theory is that it doesn't make
any predictions that are testable or
falsifiable
it simply doesn't make any such
predictions
so it is a theory that is speculative in
nature it is a beautiful theory the
mathematics is beautiful
it's very complicated but it is a theory
that is non-falsifiable
and it has not been able to make any
testable predictions
so as of now more and more people are of
the opinion more and more scientists
more and more physicists are of the
opinion
that string theory has essentially
thus far been a failure
and so right now in physics we have hit
essentially a brick wall that is
we are not able to make progress right
now for the past 30 40 years
ever since the theory of cosmological
inflation was was
proposed by alan guth after that no new
theory has come out
so that's where we are in physics right
now it is a time of crisis
in theoretical physics okay
next question
this is by legal freedom thank you very
much sir
so the question is i want to study about
champa
today's vietnam and the capital
pandurangas today
panrang yeah very interesting so this is
part of south
east asia the champa kingdom
was a vasal of the chula empire
it was a hindu shaivite kingdom in
vietnam
in southern vietnam and after the chola
empire declined
champa itself became a great maritime
empire a thalassocratic empire which
means it had a great navy
and what is now known as the so-called
south china sea
was historically always known as the
champa
because it was a champa kingdom and the
champa empire
that had complete naval control
over this particular sea so the correct
name
of the south china sea is the champa sea
and panduranga in panrang also is a very
interesting place it's another part of
southeast asia
which is hinduised which was indulged
eventually it became
it became buddhist in nature over time
so how to study this the only way to
study it is to read
articles online because there are no
books about this nobody has bothered to
write
any decent book about the these
particular kingdoms and dynasties there
are many dynasties many great kings
and if you go to these places you will
find beautiful shaywhite temples you
will find shivlingas
you will find statues of nandi you will
find great statues of
upsaras and dancers and what not
and unfortunately no historian in india
has bothered to take any interest in
this
and nobody has written books about this
so the only way to gather
information is to search online read
read scholarly articles if any uh
try to see if people have taken videos
about that you know travel videos and so
on
and and maybe look on archive.org maybe
some
ancient or older books may be present
which describe the
culture of the this era but as far as i
know
i am not aware of any good books or good
literature
about these kingdoms which is very
unfortunate
very unfortunate so i hope that in the
future indian historians
will take a greater interest in
exploring
our ancient connection with
eastern asia which is a very very rich
connection
so i hope that happens in the future in
the near future thank you for your
question
okay i will take a couple of more
questions
indic knowledge subhash chandra bose
mystery
all right so the main question is
what happened to netaji subhash chandra
bose did he die
in that alleged plane crash in formosa
in taiwan
or did he return to india and
spend the rest of his days in anonymity
so my opinion is very clear i do not
believe
the plane crash theory i believe it is
fiction
i believe that sebastian durbose had i
don't know what exactly happened to him
but i am pretty sure that he returned to
india
and the person who was later described
as described as gumnami baba
was most likely subhashin-rabos that is
my opinion
i believe anuj has done a great deal of
research about this
and i think if i'm not mistaken he has
even written a book about this
and other people have also written about
this
so there is no evidence of a plane crash
in taiwan on that date whatever it is
said and there is no evidence of
subashandra bose's ashes being there in
the rinkoji temple in japan
so these are most likely false
pieces of false evidence that were
planted to support this theory that he
died in a plane crash
most likely the person
called gum nami baba was
i would like to see the government
declassify whatever documents it has so
that we
can finally find out the truths i'm sure
the government knows what happened
so i hope it is declassified and we can
know about what happened
to this great son of india
all right
mayank thar
can you please explain the chronology of
indian history starting from ramayana
then mahabharata
and maybe even beyond that that is a
very vast
chronology but let me try and tell you
in brief
so the earliest
known phase of india's civilization
is the rig vedic phase
in which india was essentially a rural
agrarian civilization it was a culture
that did not have any cities at that
time so that talks about a time that is
most likely eight or ten thousand years
before today
that is the rig vedic phase of india
civilization and the puranas even
describe
certain events that happened before the
rigveda was written
so there was definitely something that
happened there was a phase of india
civilization that
was even before the rig vedic phase
so that is where essentially india's the
that's where our memory our collective
memory of india civilization begins
during the rig vedic and the puranic
phase after that you had the ramayana at
certain
at a certain point in time which again
was a very long time before present
then you had the mahabharata and then
you had
an urban phase of india's civilization
which is
called the harappan phase of india's
civilization
and then because of climate change the
rivers in the supper sindhu
shrunk shrank the saraswati
dried out and those great population
centers
were abandoned slowly over many
centuries it was not an abrupt event
it was a gradual abandonment of those
great population centers
and india's population moved to various
other parts of india
into interior india like gujarat
rajasthan
and further east like present-day uttar
pradesh etc
and then you had the classical
panini era of india civilization when
panini's
grammar of the sanskrit language was
written that is the time
approximately when you had the great
universities of taksha sheila nalanda
and all that and uh then you had the
gotham
then you had gotham buddha panini was
after gotham buddha most likely
so you had gotham buddha about 2500 bce
then you had the morin dynasty and then
we know what the history is of our
country
of our civilization is like because that
is reasonably well documented
you had the skeeter invasion then you
had the kushan invasion
the kushans produced great emperors like
kanishka
some of the greatest emperors we have
ever seen then you had the gupta empire
which was another great era of india's
civilization then you had some
fragmentation you had the
the invasions by the shweta hunas the
hephthalites
who invaded in numerous waves and
eventually
succeeded in conquering parts of india
and they assimilated into india's
culture and population and then
as you know the islamic invasions begin
and then we know the story
so that is a very brief
description of india's chronology
starting from the very beginning i hope
that
answers your question
all right let me take two more questions
then we'll be done for today
all right
how do we get from this is from aditya's
narration thank you
for the question how do we get from
where we are
to being 1.0 on the kardashev scale
is there a great filter between us and
being a kardashev 1.0 plus
civilization so for those of you who do
not know
the kardashev scale is a hypothetical
scale of civilizational advancement
it was uh proposed by the uh
soviet scientist astronomer
nikolai kardashev in the 1960s i believe
so there are
three uh stages on the scale
uh stage one stage two and stage three
so if you are a level one civilization
it means that you have
you have developed the means of
harnessing the entire
energy and all the resources of your
home planet
it means that you can control the
weather
you can harness all the minerals
and you can control essentially
everything that happens on the planet
and all the energy that comes out of it
so currently we are not
at kardashev 1.0 we are below that
because we still cannot control the
weather
we still cannot control the oceans
we still can't stop earthquakes we
are very energy inefficient we are still
destroying the planet because of
population uh because of overpopulation
because of pollution
and much more so we are very far
from being 1.0 on the kardashev scale
uh is there a great filter i think the
we are currently technologically very
not not quite as advanced as one would
need to be
and there are great impediments we are
not unified as as
one on the planetary scale
most of our energy and efforts are are
focused on fighting each other so if you
would use all that funding and all that
scientific advancement
in you know making the planet a better
place and
and making it safer for humanity and
solving the real problems
then we would be closer we would start
moving closer to becoming a kardashev
1.0
civilization so yes we are very far from
it right now the main filter is that we
are
so disunited we are at loggerheads with
each
with each other there are so many
geopolitical conflicts cultural
conflicts there are so many battles
for supremacy going on ideological
supremacy religious supremacy
and all that so that is essentially
taking away all our energy and focus
from where it should be
so that's why we are very far from being
a kardashev 1.0 civilization
and just fyi kardashev 2.0 means you can
means it is a civilization that can
control the
entire energy and resources of its
entire solar system
and kardashev 3 is a civilization that
can control its home galaxy
all the resources and all the energy so
that's what the kardashev
kardashian scale is about so we are very
far from being even 1.0
all right i'm going to take
one last question for today and then we
shall continue
tomorrow
uh
let me quickly find something
all right this is by samyadi chaudhary
how did indian how did ancient indian
people
scientists do research and development
where their their own labs or what
so like i said india's ancient education
system was based around
temples at the smallest scale then you
had great greater temples you had
viharas monasteries and then you had
great universities
and all of these were state funded so
the scientists and scholars did not need
to seek funding
the funding was given to them they did
not need to
work for a livelihood they all their
only
duty was to teach and and to
uh take their field of study and
research
forward so how did scientists do
research and development
so the science that we had the
technology that we had at the time
was essentially uh
hydro engineering we had navigation we
had naval ships and all that we had
great ships
india was always a seafaring
civilization
they had we had great seafarers in the
rigveda itself there are descriptions of
ships with a hundred ores so indians
used to travel have great sea voyages
in the ancient days so
there was a lot of technological
development so technological development
goes hand in hand with scientific
development so india was the most
advanced scientific
civilization of its time the
research and development was not done in
labs because we do not have
quantum physics and nuclear fission and
things like that
but indians did develop electricity
there is an ancient text which
which shows how to create a voltaic cell
so i think the whatever research and
development was done
was done at whatever level was possible
at the time
there was a great deal of astronomy so
we had astronomical research india was
the most advanced
civilization when it comes to astronomy
the ancient indian calendar is still the
most advanced calendar that humankind
has ever devised it is more accurate
than the current calendar we are using
throughout the world so india was very
advanced in astronomy astronomy needs
observational evidence so we had
observatories and much
and things like that so that is how
ancient science was done we did not have
big labs but we had universities
where scientists would get together and
they would do their work
and we had great mathematicians calculus
was first developed in
india it was not developed by newton and
and the other guy it was developed in
india at least a hundred years before
isaac newton
and trigonometry was also developed in
india in finance series were developed
in india
ayurveda the science of ayurveda which
was must have taken thousands of years
to develop
also developed in india pharmacology
toxicology and so many other sciences
they were developed in india over
centuries or millennia and eventually
all of this knowledge
made its way into the west because of
the
islamic invasions where all this
knowledge was taken out of india's
universities and libraries and the
the arabs were very happy to acknowledge
the fact that this knowledge came from
india and even
mathematicians in europe like fibonacci
they readily acknowledged
that this mathematics and this knowledge
came from india it is later that the
jesuit priests
stole more knowledge more data from
india
and they passed it off as their own
development so that's what happened
so there was a great deal of research
and development in india
not through labs but in universities
in great ancient universities
okay i will take one more question
before we finish
all right this is about geopolitics it's
from dave how can india upgrades
itself to combat china for possible
chinese threats in the future
i would say the number one thing india
needs to do is to develop a blue water
navy
the indian establishment keeps saying
that the indian ocean is our strategic
backyard
well what have you done to actually make
it your strategic backyard
do we have a navy that is sufficient to
patrol the indian ocean
region 24x7 our navy isn't even
sufficient to patrol our coastline
effectively because we have such an
enormous coastline
so india needs to invest in a blue water
navy
india needs to spend a lot
of investment in building a blue water
navy and that needs to happen very very
fast
and the strength of a navy is not
measured in the number of ships it has
it is measured by the number of missiles
you can put out at sea
on a given day so that is what india
needs to do it needs to
develop its military firepower it needs
to
ensure that there is distributed
lethality which is a very important
concept that i will explain
in another episode so i would say that
the number one thing india should do
is to develop a powerful navy and to
invest
very seriously in scientific research
and development
especially in the cyber domain and
especially in combating
bio weapons because that's what's
happening right now i'm not saying we
should develop bio weapons
but we should have the ability to
counter
threats of bio weapons so these are some
of the things that india
should do all right i'm gonna end here
thank you so much for your questions it
was wonderful
interacting with you all and we're going
to continue this tomorrow
so i think in the future going forward
we should have some theme for every
discussion for every question answer
session
so tomorrow i'm going to talk about
shingis khan
so i have made a video about changiska
and most likely you
all of you must be knowing about it so
it addresses the question of why ching
is khan refused to
invade india even though he was at
india's doorstep
so i have addressed that specific narrow
question
but there are lots of questions that
have been asked of me
and i'm sure you have many questions
there is a greater context to the story
and there is a lot of learnings that we
can learn from genghis khan as
a ruler and as a leader so that's what i
would like to
take up tomorrow so please come up with
your questions keep some questions ready
and i will answer all of your questions
about genghis khan and the mongol empire
tomorrow thank you very much and have a
good night have a good day stay safe
stay healthy
and i'll see you tomorrow bye